# Gabriele Ara, Eng

# Embedded Systems, Real-Time Systems, System Programming, Research

### ⊠ gabriele.ara@santannapisa.it ⋒ www.gabrieleara.it

© Piazza Due Giugno 15, 57122 Livorno, Italy © (+39) 338 419 1704

Gabriele Ara is a Ph.D. Student at Scuola Superiore Sant'Anna, Pisa (Italy). He has more than 10 years of experience in system programming.

Gabriele's expertise spans multiple fields in Computer and Software Engineering and IT, including embedded systems, real-time systems, scheduling, computer architectures, software design and implementation, system programming, networking, and research.

He is currently a proud member of the Real-Time Systems Lab at Scuola Superiore Sant'Anna under the supervision of Prof. Tommaso Cucinotta, and his research interests include energy-aware scheduling of real-time systems on embedded platforms running Linux, high-performance network communications in cloud environments, and the simulation of multi-core real-time systems.

Gabriele has a B.Sc. in Computer Engineering (cum laude) from the University of Pisa, Pisa (Italy), and an M.Sc. in Embedded Computing Systems Engineering (cum laude), a course jointly offered by the University of Pisa and Scuola Superiore Sant'Anna, Pisa (Italy).

Gabriele speaks fluently Italian and English (almost) alike. His colleagues describe him as analytical, creative, competitive, and goal-oriented.

### **Current Position**

Ph.D. Student, Scuola Superiore Sant'Anna, Pisa (Italy)

2019-Present

Supervisor: Prof. Tommaso Cucinotta

Research topics include Energy-Aware Scheduling of Real-Time Tasks, Dynamic Voltage and Frequency Scaling (DVFS) on Embedded Platforms, Real-Time Systems Simulation and Scheduling, and High-Performance Networking Stacks and Frameworks.

### **Experience**

**Textbook Author**, Zanichelli editore S.p.A (Italy)

2013-Present

Gabriele writes from time to time chapters and sections of IT textbooks in Italian. The chapters focus on mobile application development essentials for Android OS, from the very basics to more advanced use-case examples.

### **High School Teaching Professional**

2018-2019

Istituto di Istruzione Superiore "Vespucci-Colombo", Livorno (Italy)

For one academic year, Gabriele worked as a part-time professor in an Italian high school, teaching IT and IT Laboratory to both 10th and 11th-grade students.

#### **E-learning Technical Specialist**, University of Pisa, Pisa (Italy)

2017-2018

To support my studies, I worked a couple of years as on-site support to technical and teaching personnel for the University for practical aspects of live streaming classes and conferences and the post-production of videos of an e-learning platform. Duties included managing recording equipment, streaming software, and providing hands-on support in case of live failures.

**Tutor**, Independent Contractor, Livorno (Italy)

2013-2018

Throughout my university years, I managed to help some high school students in STEM fields as their tutor, helping them with assignments in classes such as Computer Engineering, IT, Maths, Electronics, and Physics.

### **Awards**

Best Paper Award 2020

Gabriele Ara, Tommaso Cucinotta, Luca Abeni, Carlo Vitucci, for the work "Comparative Evaluation of Kernel Bypass Mechanisms for High-performance Inter-container Communications" at the 10th International Conference on Cloud Computing and Services Science (CLOSER), 2020

### **Education**

Master of Science (M.Sc.) in Embedded Computing Systems University of Pisa and Scuola Superiore Sant'Anna, Pisa (Italy)	2019
Bachelor of Science (B.Sc.) in Computer Engineering University of Pisa, Pisa (Italy)	2016
Secondary Diploma as IT Professional Istituto Tecnico Industriale Statale G. Galilei, Livorno (Italy)	2013

### **Supervision**

Leonardo Lai 2019

Master student in Embedded Computing Systems, Scuola Superiore Sant'Anna, Pisa (Italy)
Subject of the dissertation: Implementation and Evaluation of High-Performance Userspace Networking
Mechanisms for Virtualized Network Functions

### **Professional Skills**

**Communication skills** Comfortable interacting with people with cross-cultural backgrounds from around the world. Gave presentations to moderate international audiences for conferences and workshops. Can communicate strengths and weaknesses of his work.

**Organisational/Managerial skills** Can both work in small teams and manage to get things done by himself. Comfortable leading other people when necessary to organize the work. Excellent debugging and investigative skills for software/computer systems.

#### Job-related skills

Following is the list of known programming languages and tools organized by proficiency level.

### **Excellent knowledge and proficiency:**

• **C/C++**, including the understanding of language internals, standard libraries, POSIX, Linux-specific libraries, Linux system programming, microcontrollers programming.

#### Proficient knowledge:

- Virtualization technologies, including Docker, LXC, LXD, and custom solutions based on cgroups and namespaces:
- High-Performance Networking frameworks, including DPDK, FD.io VPP, Open vSwitch;
- Linux management and administrative tools for machine configuration and troubleshooting.
- Unix-based systems command line, scripting in Sh and Bash;
- · Java (standard libraries, JavaFX, Spring, Apache and Servlet libraries);
- Android App programming (using Java+XML);

### Good knowledge:

- · Linux kernel internals and hacking;
- · JavaScript (standard libraries, JQuery, D3);
- Matlab and Simulink for scripting, data analysis, and system control or simulation;
- Web development using HTML5, PHP5, CSS3, XML, JSON, REST patterns;
- **SQL** and MySQL software suite;
- · CISCO technologies and CISCO IOS;

### Languages

Italian: Native proficiency

English: Full professional proficiency

### **Personal Interests**

## **Publications**

Search me on Google Scholar for the list of my peer-reviewed conference proceedings and journals. Or have a look at my publications page.